And it was these same women, when I decided to wear my hijab, who supported me through it. And when I was bullied for being Muslim, I always felt like I had an army of unapologetic North African aunties who had my back. And so every morning at 15, I would wake up and stand in front of a mirror, and wrap beautiful bright silk around my head
Y fueron estas mismas mujeres, cuando decidí llevar mi hiyab, las que me apoyaron. Y cuando sufrí acoso por ser musulmana, siempre me pareció que tenía un ejército de tías norteafricanas que me apoyaban. Así que cada mañana, cuando tenía 15 años, me levantaba, me ponía delante de un espejo y me cubría la cabeza con una seda preciosa y brillante,
the way my mother does and my grandmother did. And one day that summer 2009, I stepped out into the streets of New York City on my way to volunteer at a domestic violence organization that a woman in my neighborhood had started. And I remember at that moment I felt a yank at the back of my head. Then someone pulled and grabbed me, trying to remove my hijab from off of my head. I turned around to a tall, broad-shouldered man,
igual que lo hace mi madre y que lo hacía mi abuela. Y un día, en el verano de 2009, iba por las calles de Nueva York para hacer de voluntaria en una organización contra la violencia doméstica que había creado una mujer de mi barrio. Y recuerdo que en ese momento sentí un tirón en la parte trasera de mi cabeza. Luego alguien tiró y me agarró, intentando quitarme el hiyab de la cabeza. Me di la vuelta y vi a un hombre alto y ancho de espaldas,
pure hate in his eyes. I struggled and fought back, and finally was able to get away, hid myself in the bathroom of that organization and cried and cried. I kept thinking to myself, "Why does he hate me? He doesn't even know me." Hate crimes against Muslims in the US increased by 1,600 percent post-9/11, and one in every four women in the US will suffer some form of gender violence. And it may not seem like it, but Islamophobia and anti-Muslim violence is a form of gender violence, given the visibility of Muslim women in our hijabs. And so I was not alone, and that horrified me. It made me want to do something. It made me want to go out there and make sure that no one I loved, that no woman would have to feel this insecure in her own skin. So I started to think about how the women in my own neighborhood were able to build community for themselves, and how they were able to use the very little resources they had to actually offer something. And I began to think about what I could potentially offer to build safety and power for women. And through this journey, I learned a couple of things, and this is what I want to share with you today, some of these lessons. So lesson number one: start with what you know.
sus ojos llenos de odio puro. Luché y peleé y al final pude escapar, me escondí en el baño de la organización y lloré sin parar. No paraba de pensar, "¿Por qué me odia? Ni siquiera me conoce". Los crímenes de odio contra los musulmanes en EE. UU. aumentaron un 1600 % después del 11-S, y una de cada cuatro mujeres en EE. UU. sufrirá algún tipo de violencia de género. Y puede que no lo parezca, pero la islamofobia y la violencia contra musulmanes es un tipo de violencia de género, dada la visibilidad de las mujeres musulmanas con los hiyabs. Así que no estaba sola y eso me aterraba. Me hizo querer hacer algo. Me hizo querer salir ahí fuera y asegurarme de que nadie a quien amara, que ninguna mujer tuviera que sentirse así de insegura en su propia piel. Así que empecé a pensar en cómo las mujeres de mi propio barrio fueron capaces de construir una comunidad para ellas, y cómo pudieron utilizar los pocos recursos que tenían para de verdad ofrecer algo. Y comencé a pensar qué podría ofrecer yo para construir seguridad y poder para las mujeres. Y a lo largo de este viaje aprendí algunas cosas, y eso es lo que quiero compartir hoy con Uds., algunas de esas lecciones. Lección número uno: comiencen con lo que conocen.
At the time, I had been doing Shotokan karate for as long as I could remember, and so I had a black belt. Yeah. And so, I thought -- surprise. (Laughter) I thought that maybe I should go out into my neighborhood and teach self-defense to young girls. And so I actually went out and knocked on doors, spoke to community leaders, to parents, to young women, and finally was able to secure a free community center basement and convince enough young women that they should come to my class. And it actually all worked out, because when I pitched the idea, most of the responses were, like, "All right, cute, this 5'1" hijabi girl who knows karate. How nice." But in reality, I became the Queens, New York version of Mr. Miyagi at 16 years old, and I started teaching 13 young women in that community center basement self-defense. And with every single self-defense move, for eight sessions over the course of that summer, we began to understand the power of our bodies, and we began to share our experiences about our identities. And sometimes there were shocking realizations, and other times there were tears, but mostly it was laughs. And I ended that summer with this incredible sisterhood, and I began to feel much safer in my own skin. And it was because of these women that we just kept teaching.
En ese momento, yo llevaba haciendo karate Shotokan. desde que tenía memoria, así que era cinturón negro. Sí. Así que pensé... sorpresa. (Risas) Pensé que quizás debería ir a mi barrio a enseñar defensa propia a las chicas jóvenes. Y de hecho fui y llamé a las puertas, hablé con los líderes de la comunidad, con padres, con mujeres jóvenes y al final pude conseguir gratis un sótano del centro comunitario y convencer a suficientes mujeres para que vinieran a mi clase. Y la verdad es que funcionó, porque cuando propuse la idea casi todas las respuestas fueron en plan, "Vale, qué linda, esta chica de 1,55 m. con hiyab sabe karate. Qué simpática". En realidad, me convertí en la versión neoyorkina de Queens del Sr. Miyagi con solo 16 años, y empecé a enseñar en el sótano del centro comunitario a 13 chicas jóvenes defensa propia. Y con cada movimiento de defensa propia, durante ocho sesiones a lo largo de ese verano, empezamos a entender el poder de nuestros cuerpos y a compartir nuestras experiencias sobre nuestras identidades. A veces tuvimos conclusiones sorprendentes y otras veces hubo lágrimas, pero sobre todo hubo risas. Ese verano acabé con una hermandad increíble y empecé a sentirme mucho más segura en mi propia piel. Y fue por esas mujeres a las que no parábamos de enseñar.
I never thought that I would continue, but we just kept teaching. And today, nine years, 17 cities, 12 countries, 760 courses and thousands of women and girls later, I'm still teaching. And what started as a self-defense course in the basement of a community center is now an international grassroots organization focused on building safety and power for women around the world: Malikah. (Applause) Now, for lesson number two: start with who you know. Oftentimes, it could be quite exciting, especially if you're an expert in something and you want to have impact, to swoop into a community and think you have the magic recipe. But very early on I learned that, as esteemed philosopher Kendrick Lamar once said, it's really important to be humble and to sit down. So, basically, at 15 years old,
Nunca pensé que seguiría, pero seguimos enseñando. Y hoy, nueve años, 17 ciudades, 12 países, 760 cursos y miles de mujeres y niñas después, todavía sigo enseñando. Y lo que comenzó como un curso de defensa personal en el sótano de un centro comunitario ahora es el origen de una organización internacional centrada en construir seguridad y poder para las mujeres de todo el mundo: Malikah. (Aplausos) Y ahora la lección número dos: comiencen con quienes ya conocen. A menudo puede ser muy emocionante, sobre todo, si son expertos en algo y quieren causar impacto, entrar de golpe en una comunidad pensando que tienen una receta mágica. Pero muy pronto aprendí que, como dijo el apreciado filósofo Kendrick Lamar, es muy importante ser humilde y sentarse. Así que básicamente, con 15 años,
the only community that I had any business doing work with were the 14-year-old girls in my neighborhood, and that's because I was friends with them. Other than that, I didn't know what it meant to be a child of Bengali immigrants in Brooklyn or to be Senegalese in the Bronx. But I did know young women who were connected to those communities, and it was quite remarkable how they already had these layers of trust and awareness and relationship with their communities. So like my mother and the women in her neighborhood, they had these really strong social networks, and it was about providing capacity and believing in other women's definition of safety. Even though I was a self-defense instructor, I couldn't come into a community and define safety for any other woman who was not part of my own community. And it was because, as our network expanded, I learned that self-defense is not just physical. It's actually really emotional work. I mean, we would do a 60-minute self-defense class, and then we'd have 30 minutes reserved for just talking and healing. And in those 30 minutes, women would share what brought them to the class to begin with but also various other experiences with violence. And, as an example, one time in one of those classes, one woman actually started to talk about the fact that she had been in a domestic violence relationship for over 30 years, and it was her first time being able to articulate that because we had established that safe space for her. So it's powerful work, but it only happens when we believe in women's agency to define what safety and what power looks like for themselves. All right, for lesson number three -- and this was the hardest thing for me -- the most important thing about this work is to start with the joy. When I started doing this work, I was reacting to a hate-based attack, so I was feeling insecure and anxious and overwhelmed. I was really afraid. And it makes sense, because if you take a step back, and I can imagine that a lot of women in this room can probably relate to this, the feeling, an overwhelming feeling of insecurity, is oftentimes with us constantly. I mean, imagine this: walking home late at night, hearing footsteps behind you. You wonder if you should walk faster or if you should slow down. You keep your keys in your hand in case you need to use them. You say, "Text me when you get home. I want to make sure you are safe." And we mean those words. We're afraid to put down our drinks. We're afraid to speak too much or too little in a meeting. And imagine being woman and black and trans and queer and Latinx and undocumented and poor and immigrant, and you could then only imagine how overwhelming this work can be, especially within the context of personal safety. However, when I took a step to reflect on what brought me to this work to begin with, I began to realize it was actually the love that I had for women in my community. It was the way I saw them gather, their ability to build for each other, that inspired me to keep doing this work day in and day out. So whether I was in a refugee camp in Jordan or a community center in Dallas, Texas or a corporate office in Silicon Valley, women gathered in beautifully magical ways and they built together and supported each other in ways that shifted culture to empower and build safety for women. And that is how the change happens. It was through those relationships we built together. That's why we don't just teach self-defense, but we also throw dance parties and host potlucks and write love notes to each other and sing songs together. And it's really about the friendship, and it's been so, so fun. So the last thing I want to leave you with is that the key takeaway for me in teaching self-defense all of these years is that I actually don't want women, as cool as the self-defense moves are, to go out and use these self-defense techniques. I don't want any woman to have to de-escalate any violent situation. But for that to happen, the violence shouldn't happen, and for the violence not to happen,
la única comunidad con la tenía algún asunto eran las chicas de 14 años de mi barrio, y eso se debía a que éramos amigas. Aparte de eso, no sabía qué significaba ser la hija de inmigrantes bengalíes en Brooklyn o ser senegalesa en el Bronx. Pero sí que conocía a chicas jóvenes conectadas a esas comunidades, y era bastante reseñable cómo ya tenían esas capas de confianza, conciencia y relación con sus comunidades. Al igual que mi madre y que las mujeres de su barrio, tenían unas redes sociales muy fuertes que giraban en torno a proveer capacidad y creer en la definición de seguridad de otras mujeres. A pesar de que yo era monitora de defensa personal, no podía llegar a una comunidad y definir la seguridad de cualquier mujer que no era parte de mi comunidad. Y se debía a que, a medida que nuestra red aumentaba aprendí que la defensa personal no es solo física. En realidad, es un trabajo muy emocional. Me refiero a que teníamos una clase de defensa personal de 60 minutos y luego reservábamos 30 minutos para hablar y curarnos. Y en esos 30 minutos, las mujeres compartían lo que les había llevado a esa clase, pero también compartían otras experiencias con la violencia. Y, como ejemplo, una vez en una de esas clases, una mujer comenzó a hablar sobre el hecho de que llevaba 30 años en una relación de violencia doméstica, y era la primera vez que era capaz de expresarlo porque le habíamos facilitado un espacio seguro. Es un trabajo poderoso, pero solo sucede cuando creemos en la capacidad de las mujeres para definir lo que significan para ellas la seguridad y el poder. Vale, respecto a la lección número tres... y esto fue lo más difícil para mí... lo más importante en ese trabajo es empezar con alegría. Cuando comencé en este trabajo estaba reaccionando a un ataque basado en el odio así que me sentía insegura, ansiosa y agobiada. Me daba mucho miedo. Y tiene sentido, porque si dan un paso atrás, y puedo imaginar que muchas mujeres en esta sala se sienten identificadas, el sentimiento, un sentimiento de inseguridad abrumador, a menudo está con nosotras constantemente. Quiero decir, imaginen esto: de camino a casa de noche, tarde, oyen pasos detrás de Uds. Se preguntan si deberían andar más rápido o más despacio. Tienen las llaves en la mano por si acaso las necesitan. Dicen: "Escríbeme cuando llegues a casa. Quiero asegurarme de que llegas bien". Y lo decimos de verdad. Nos da miedo soltar nuestras bebidas. Nos da miedo hablar demasiado o muy poco en una reunión. E imaginen que son una mujer negra, trans, homosexual, "Latinx", indocumentada, pobre e inmigrante, y entonces podrán imaginar cómo de apabullante puede ser este trabajo, sobre todo, en el contexto de seguridad personal. Sin embargo, cuando di un paso para reflexionar sobre qué me llevó de primeras a este trabajo, me di cuenta de que en realidad era el amor que sentía por las mujeres de mi comunidad. Fue la manera en la que vi que se reunían, su habilidad de construir para todas, lo que me inspiró a seguir con este trabajo día sí y día también. Así que tanto si estaba en un campo de refugiados en Jordania o en un centro comunitario en Dallas, Texas, o en una oficina de Silicon Valley, las mujeres se reunían de una manera mágica y preciosa y construían juntas y se apoyaba unas a otras de maneras que cambiaban nuestra cultura para dar poder a las mujeres y otorgarles seguridad. Y así es como sucede el cambio. A través de esas relaciones pudimos construir juntas. Por eso no enseñamos solo defensa propia, sino que también organizamos bailes y cenas comunitarias y escribimos notitas de amor para todas y cantamos canciones. En realidad, todo gira entorno a la amistad y está siendo muy, muy, divertido. Lo último que quiero contarles es que la moraleja de haber enseñado defensa personal todos estos años es que no quiero que las mujeres, por geniales que sean los movimientos de defensa, salgan y usen esas técnicas de defensa propia. No quiero que ninguna mujer tenga que rebajar ninguna situación violenta. Pero para que eso pase, la violencia no debería suceder, y para que la violencia no suceda,
the systems and the cultures that allow for this violence to take place to begin with needs to stop. And for that to happen, we need all hands on deck. So I've given you my secret recipe, and now it's up to you. To start with what you know, to start with who you know and to start with joy. But just start. Thank you so much. (Applause)
los sistemas y las culturas que para empezar permiten que ocurra esta violencia tienen que parar. Y para que eso ocurra, todos tenemos que arrimar el hombro. Yo les he dado mi receta secreta, y ahora les toca a Uds. Empiecen con lo que conocen, empiecen con quienes conocen y empiecen con alegría. Pero empiecen. Muchísimas gracias. (Aplausos)